Contact

www.linkedin.com/in/ petersomerville (LinkedIn)

Top Skills

Customer Relations
Product Vision
Product Road Mapping

Certifications

Managing Jira Projects: 3 Helpful Concepts and Features Prepare for the Atlassian Managing Jira Projects (ACP-620) Certification Lean Six Sigma Foundations Learning GitHub Value Proposition Design

Honors-Awards

Veteran of the Day
Navy and Marine Corps
Achievement Medal with Combat "V"

Peter Somerville

Co-Founder @ Caparra | Smarter DevOps Minneapolis, Minnesota, United States

Summary

Peter Somerville is the co-founder of Caparra, a Minneapolis-based startup building Al-powered tools that help software teams work together and improve code quality.

Experienced in project management, fundraising, communications, and customer acquisition, Peter has been a leader with fin-tech startups, angel investor networks, and an advisor to cybersecurity, medical technology, and education startups. Peter is a combat-proven leader with a passion for building teams and applying innovation to improve lives. He began his career as an infantry officer in the United States Marine Corps, leading Marines in Iraq. Since his time in uniform, Peter has applied his leadership skills to build tech startups, nonprofit charities, and political campaigns.

A Minnesota native, Peter earned an MBA from the University of Minnesota and a bachelor's degree from Yale University. In 2017, Peter was recognized as National Veteran of the Day by the U.S. Department of Veteran Affairs. An avid traveler, Peter has visited more than 40 countries, hiked 2,500 miles in Spain, Portugal, and France, and enjoys speaking conversational French, Spanish, and German.

Experience

Caparra
Co-Founder
2024 - Present (1 year)
Minneapolis, Minnesota, United States

Caparra is a Minneapolis-based startup building Al-powered tools that help software teams eliminate toil, improve code quality, and reduce tech debt -- automatically.

Caparra is the creator of Zumbro for GitHub, a DevOps automation tool that helps teams define, apply, and enforce engineering standards without adding overhead. If you're ready to improve teamwork, reduce technical debt, and ship better code faster, Zumbro will help you make it happen, right inside your GitHub workflow.

In Fall 2024, Caparra worked with Launch MN at the University of Minnesota, a statewide effort to support entrepreneurs and nurture tech startups with a goal of fostering Minnesota's innovation ecosystem.

Self-employed Customer Development Consultant 2020 - 2024 (4 years)

- Consulted with early-stage startups and entrepreneurs to identify and target customer segments
- Served cybersecurity, medical technology, and education clients in the United States, Europe, and Asia
- Visited 20 countries, learned conversational Spanish and French, and hiked
 2,000 miles in Spain, Portugal, and France

xx network Head of Node and Developer Relations

2019 - 2020 (1 year)

- Built and managed node and developer communities for the "xx network" and "xx coin", a privacy-protecting blockchain and cryptocurrency led by pioneering cryptographer David Chaum
- Directed communications to public and investors for initial public sale of tokens, including moderating eight two-hour live webinars explaining innovative cryptography, token economics, and decentralized networks
- Co-authored Whitepaper and other technical papers, presenting advanced cryptographic concepts in an accessible and compelling format for general readers
- Built decentralized community of 600 node operators and 100+ distributed application developers
- Authored 30+ press releases and blog posts to establish company voice in blockchain marketplace

Gopher Angels MBA Associate 2018 - 2019 (1 year)

Greater Minneapolis-St. Paul Area

- Assisted in due diligence review of three seed round investments in earlystage startups for Minnesota's largest network of angel investors
- Facilitated communications between 80 angel investors and pipeline of entrepreneurs seeking funding
- Co-managed logistics for bimonthly evening of pitch meetings

StreetShares (Acquired by MeridianLink; NYSE: MLNK)
Director of Investor Relations
2014 - 2018 (4 years)

Washington D.C. Metro Area

- Led investor product design, customer acquisition, and customer service at a marketplace lending startup offering financial services to military and veteran community, from launch to Series B round
- Nurtured population of retail, accredited, and institutional investors from 40 to more than 10,000 members
- Drafted all communications with investor members in heavily-regulated US financial services industry
- Represented company at 30+ public speaking opportunities, training sessions, and pitch competitions
- Raised \$175,000 in grants for the StreetShares Foundation, a nonprofit supporting veteran entrepreneurship
- Pioneered partnerships with several dozen organizations and leaders in military and veteran services, small business finance and entrepreneurship, and personal finance and investing

Tommy Moll for Congress Campaign Manager 2013 - 2014 (1 year)

Hot Springs, Arkansas

- Managed from beginning-to-end all aspects of a US Congressional campaign that raised more than \$600,000 with first-time candidate
- Forged relationships with key donors, grassroots leaders, and community members across 33 counties
- Directed all public communications via paid and earned media, built relationships with Arkansas and national reporters and press outlets and controlled all web-based, email, and social media communications
- Recruited, trained, and deployed more than 100 volunteers who made over 11,000 phone calls to voters

 Devised and implemented accounting systems in compliance with federal, state, and local election laws

Teneo Network Executive Director 2012 - 2013 (1 year)

Austin, Texas

- Directed content development, member recruitment, and donor outreach as sole employee of a young nonprofit organization
- Guided Board of Directors in strategic planning process to identify and pursue organizational goals
- Planned, coordinated, and executed a four-day retreat for 200 members and guests with over 100 scheduled events, panels, guided conversations, and exercises in personal and professional development
- Supervised volunteer leaders of 10 regional chapters in producing dinners and network-building events
- Built relationships with top donors and leaders in politics, business, and arts

Charles Koch Foundation Grants Coordinator 2009 - 2011 (2 years)

Washington D.C. Metro Area

- Oversaw drafting, timely processing, and legal compliance of grants to 200+ universities and nonprofits
- Transitioned grants process to a Salesforce database, creating a digital archive of all grants, improving measurement records, financial and compliance verification, and knowledge sharing across all teams
- Project Manager for transition to an online application connected to the foundation's online database, allowing foundation to handle nearly 200 job and internship applications per month

United States Marine Corps
4 years

Aide-de-Camp to the Commanding General, 1st Marine Division 2007 - 2008 (1 year)

Camp Pendleton, CA

- Personal assistant to leader of a 25,000-member Marine division
- Arranged transportation, logistics, and accompanied General on more than 20 multi-day trips within the continental US, to Hawaii, Guam, and combat areas of Iraq and Afghanistan

• Planned and supervised execution of the General's schedule in accordance with his strategic priorities

Executive Officer, Headquarters and Service Company, 2nd Battalion, 4th Marines

2007 - 2007 (less than a year)

Camp Pendleton, CA

- Developed six-month pre-deployment training plan for 240 Marines to acquire combat skills
- Supervised maintenance and inventory of 800+ pieces of military equipment with a value of \$5 million

Platoon Commander, Echo Company, 2nd Battalion, 4th Marines 2006 - 2007 (1 year)

Ramadi, Iraq

- Led a 44-Marine infantry platoon in five months of urban combat in Western Iraq
- Trained and commanded Marines on more than 100 combat missions to support fellow Marines under enemy fire, and to rapidly evacuate injured personnel to receive medical treatment
- Designed and implemented daily resupply of food, water, and ammunition for
 180 Marines in a combat zone for five months

Student Officer 2004 - 2006 (2 years) Quantico, Virginia

U.S. House of Representatives, Office of Congressman Jim Ramstad

Interim Deputy District Director 2004 - 2004 (less than a year)

Greater Minneapolis-St. Paul Area

- Briefed, staffed, and drove Congressman for all meetings and visits in his suburban Minneapolis district
- Ran Congressman's military service academy nomination program

Education

University of Minnesota - Carlson School of Management Master of Business Administration - MBA · (2020)

Yale University
B.A., Philosophy · (2004)

Edina Senior High School